اَعُوْذُ بِاللهِ مِنَّ الشِّيْطَانِ الرَّجِيْمِ۝
بِسْمِ اللهِ الرَّحْمَانِ الرَّحِيْمَ۝
اَلْحَمْدُ لله  وَالصَّلَاةُ وَالسَّلَامُ عَلى سَيِّدِنَا محمد وَعَلَى اَلِهِ وَصَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ تَسْلِيْمًا كَثِيْرا
Rasool Allah ﷺ was delivering a Khut'ba(خطبة), and he said;
إنَّ الله خيرا عبدًا مِن عباده بين الدنيا وبين ما عندالله فختارا ذالك العبد ما عندالله
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ has given one of His slaves, two choices.
The first choice is to stay in this world.
The second choice is to leave to die
and to go to what Allah سبحانه وتعالى has for that person in the afterlife
and that slave has chosen the latter.
That slave has chosen to go to what Allah has reserved for him in the afterlife.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه started crying.
Abu Saeed Al-Khudri(أبوسعيدألخدري) one of the Ansaar(أنْصَار). He said:
We looked at Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) and we couldn't figure out, why he is crying.
It doesn't seem to be something very emotional about that statement.
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ has given one of His slaves, the choice of staying in Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) or leaving Duniyah(دُنِيَّا),
given him the choice of living longer, or dying.
So, why is Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) crying?
Abu Saeed Al-Khudri(أبوسعيدألخدري) said;
But then we came to know why he cried
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه was the only one among us
who understood what Rasool Allah ﷺ meant.
Rasool Allah ﷺ was actually talking about himself.
He was that slave of Allah.
But you see Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه because of the fact that he has spent so much time with Rasool Allah ﷺ
more than anyone else among the Sahabah(صحابه)
he could understand Rasool Allah ﷺ better and more than anybody else.
And he can get the message sometimes without Rasool Allah ﷺ even speaking it
because they have been friends for their entire lives.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه was weeping, and then Rasool Allah ﷺ said the following,
إنَّ أمنَّ الناس عليَّ في صحبته ، وماله أبوبكر
The one, who has done me, the greatest favors
through his friendship to me, and his wealth, is Abu Bakr(ابوبكر).
Now imagine Rasool Allah ﷺ saying this towards the end of his life in front of all of the Sahabah(صحابه)
an admission, a recognition of his close friend and companion, Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه.
He is saying that he has done me so many favors.
In fact another Hadith(حديث),  Rasool Allah ﷺ says;
Every one of you, who has done me a favor, I have paid them back except Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق).
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
ولو كنت متخذً خليلً غير ربي لتخذت ابابكر خليل
ولكن أخوة الإسلام ومودة لا يبقين في المسجد باب إلَّا سدَّا إلَّا باب أبي بكرٍ رواه البخاري
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: And if I were to take a Khalil(خليل)
a Khalil(خليل) is something higher than a Sahib(صاحب), a Sahib(صاحب) is a friend
Khalil(خليل) is a higher level of friendship, very close.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: If I was to take a Khalil(خليل) besides Allah
it would be Abu Bakr(ابوبكر).
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ is saying that I'm the Khalil(خليل) of Allah
that he is the Khalil(خليل) of Allah.
Rasool Allah ﷺ is the Khalil(خليل) of Allah.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
If I were to be a Khalil(خليل) of someone else, it would be Abu Bakr(ابوبكر)
but between us is Akhuwat-Tul-Islam(أخوة الإسلام)
the brotherhood of Islam Wa-Muwaddato(ومودةُ) and the love of Islam.
That's the relationship between me and Abu Bakr(ابوبكر).
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ said, you know, in the Masjid-e-Nabawi(مسجد النبوي).
The Sahabah(صحابه), particularly the Muhajireen(مهاجرين) they were given small pieces of land next to the Masjid(مسجد).
So they would build their houses, right next to the walls of Masjid-e-Nabawi(مسجد النبوي)
and they would open for themselves very small gates
so that they could immediately walk from their house to the Masjid(مسجد).
So, these were private doors of some of the Sahabah(صحابه)
and there are quite a few of them, Rasool Allah ﷺ said:
And I want all of these private doors to be closed except for the door of Abu Bakr(ابوبكر).
That's the privilege that only goes to Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه
the one who will have a private entrance into Al-Masjid-e-Nabawi(ألمسجد النبوي).
Imagine having your private gate, no one gets in except you.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: All of them should be closed
except the gate of Abu Bakr(ابوبكر)
and this is in Bukhari(بخاريْ).
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه got the message that Rasool Allah ﷺ is towards the end of his life.
Rasool Allah ﷺ became ill
that was a few months after he came back from Hajjat-Ul-Widaa(حجة الوداع).
Rasool Allah ﷺ, his illness was getting worse and worse
and he was unable to join in Salaat-Ul-Jama'at(صلوات الجماعة).
So he said:
مُرُوا أبَا بَكْرٍ أنْ يُصَلِّيَ بالنَّاسِ،
Instruct Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) to be the Imam(اِمَام), in Salah(صلاة).
Ayesha رضي الله عنها when she heard that she was trying to change the mind of Muhammadﷺ.
She said;
إنَّ أبي رجلٌ أصيف
My father is very soft hearted
and if he stands in your place, he will break down.
It's not easy to be standing in the same place of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
She said: If he stands in that position, He might break down, he's very soft hearted.
So, why don't you tell Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) to take that position.
In reality, Ayesha رضي الله عنها also had another reason for not wanting her father to be there
to give you an example to draw the point closer.
Imagine that you came a very long distance to hear Khut'ba(خطبة) from a very well known scholar.
There's an ad that says that this very well known scholar is coming into town
and he's going to give Khut'ba(خطبة).
So you come from all over London to attend this Khut'ba(خطبة).
And then you come there, and we find that it's not this scholar you came to hear, its someone else
you're not gonna like that.
Ayesha رضي الله عنها was thinking that this is a place where the people are expecting Rasool Allah ﷺ to be.
So when they see my father, they're not gonna like that.
They're used to Rasool Allah ﷺ leading them that position.
So she wanted to change the mind of Rasool Allah ﷺ, she said;
Why don't you have Umar(عُمَر) do it?
Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
مُرُوا أبَا بَكْرٍ أنْ يُصَلِّيَ بالنَّاسِ،
Instruct Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) to be the Imam(اِمَام)
She again suggested otherwise, Rasool Allah ﷺ the third time said;
إنَّكُنَّ لَأَنْتُنَّ صَوَاحِبُات يُوسُفَ،
You're like the woman of Yousuf(يوسف)
tell Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) to lead the people in Salah(صلاة).
What Rasool Allah ﷺ meant by the woman of Yousuf(يوسف)?
The woman of Yousuf(يوسف) they showed something they didn't really mean they had a different motive.
So Rasool Allah ﷺ felt that there is a different motive here why she doesn't want her father to be the Imam(اِمَام).
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه became the Imam(اِمَام) of the Muslims for a few days,
he was leading them in Salah(صلاة).
And by the way, Abul Hasan Al-Ash'ari(أبوالحسن ألأشعري)
he uses this as an evidence that Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه is the greatest scholar in this Ummah(امة),
he says because Rasool Allah ﷺ says that the one, who should lead the Salah(صلاة)
is the one, who has most knowledge in the book of Allah.
So since Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) was told to lead the Muslims in Salah(صلاة)
it's not just because he's the friend of Rasool Allah ﷺ and he is close companion
but also because he has the most Fiqh(فقه).
The deepest knowledge in Islam or understanding in Islam
and Ibn Kathir(اِبْنِ كَثِيْر), he comments on these words of Abul Hasan Al-Ash'ari(أبوالحسن ألأشعري) and says;
This should be written in letters of gold.
They're very valuable words in proving that Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) is in fact the most scholarly person in this Ummah(امة).
One day Rasool Allah ﷺ felt better.
He was still very exhausted and Rasool Allah ﷺ was once touched by Abdullah Ibn Masood(عبدالله إبن مسعود).
So he saw that the temperature of Rasool Allah ﷺ was very high so he said:
O Messenger of Allah, you have a very strong fever.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: Yes! We the prophets, our fever is double the fever of everyone else.
And Rasool Allah ﷺ says;
أشدُّ النَّاسِ بلاءً ، الأنبياءُ ، فا الأمثلُ فالأمثلُ ،
The people, who go through the most severe tests are the Prophets
and then it goes down, according to your level.
So the greater a person is and the closer they are to Allah, the more difficult the test would be.
Just like when you take an exam
there are some questions that only an A student would be able to handle
not everybody else would be able to handle them.
And there are some questions who're only the A plus could answer
because these are very difficult questions.
So Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ puts the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء) through some very difficult tests.
Now the narrator of the Hadith(حديث) said;
And I could see Rasool Allah ﷺ being carried by two men Al-Abbas(العباس) and Ali Ibn Abi Talib رضي الله عنه.
وقدماه تخطان في الأرض
And his feet are dragging on the ground that was how ill Rasool Allah ﷺ was he can't even move his feet
and he is carried by the two companions, رضي الله عنهم.
They already started the Salah(صلاة).
So when Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه saw Rasool Allah ﷺ coming he retreated
he wanted to go back.
Rasool Allah ﷺ waved to him and told him to stay where you are
and then Rasool Allah ﷺ came and sat next to Abu Bakr(ابوبكر)
and he started leading him in Salah(صلاة).
So Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) is following Rasool Allah ﷺ
and the Sahabah(صحابه) are following Abu Bakr(ابوبكر)
and then Rasool Allah ﷺ went back again.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه carried on leading the Mo'mineen(مؤمنين) in Salah(صلاة),
until it was Monday the 12 of Rabiul-Awwal(ربيع الأول).
In Salaat-Ul-Fajr(صلاةالافجر) Rasool Allah ﷺ opened his curtain and he was standing,
and he took a look at the Sahabah(صحابه) in Salah(صلاة)
the room of Ayesha(عائشه) was right there, touching the Masjid(مسجد).
So the only thing separating the room from the Masjid(مسجد) was a curtain.
Rasool Allah ﷺ uncovered that curtain
and he took a look at the Sahabah(صحابه) praying in Salaat-Ul-Fajr(صلاةالافجر)
the Masjid(مسجد) is full and Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه is reciting Qur'an in Salah(صلاة).
When Rasool Allah ﷺ saw that he smiled and you could see happiness in his face
so the narrator of the Hadith(حديث) said;
The face of Rasool Allah ﷺ became like a plate of silver,
it was shining with light.
Rasool Allah ﷺ was so happy because Rasool Allah ﷺ was now seeing the fruit of his harvest.
He is seeing the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم, performing the Salah(صلاة)
the greatest duty in Islam.
So Rasool Allah ﷺ was seeing with his own eyes the success of his message.
Rasool Allah ﷺ was the most successful of all of the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء) of Allah
with other Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء), when they pass away their Ummah(امة) cannot carry on after them.
They go down, down, down, until they reached to the bottom
and then Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ has to send another Nabi(نَبِي) to bring them up.
With Bannu Israel(بنواسرائيل) at a particular time they had 70 Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء) at one moment,
to keep them on the straight path
but Rasool Allah ﷺ has succeeded in his message so well to the extent that there's no need for a prophet after him
and his students are so successful. As Allah سبحانه وتعالى said;
كُنتُمْ خَيْرَ أُمَّةٍ أُخْرِجَتْ لِلنَّاسِ
You're the best Ummah(امة) brought forth for mankind
that they will carry on with His message, carrying the banner of Islam until the day of judgment.
Rasool Allah ﷺ says;
لا تَزالُ طائفةٌ مِن أُمَّتي على الحقِّ
There will remain a group of my Ummah(امة) on straight path until the day of judgment,
until they end up fighting with Ad-Dajjal(ألدجال).
So Rasool Allah ﷺ was so happy
that he felt now he is ready to leave, his mission is completed.
He can entrust the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم with the responsibility
with appointing their own leader, with carrying on the message of Islam.
And that's why the face of Rasool Allah ﷺ was shining and he was smiling and so happy.
As-Sahabi(صحابي) said:
وَكِدنا نُفتَنُ عن صلاتِنا
When we saw Rasool Allah ﷺ, when we saw his face
we were about to forget about our Salah(صلاة).
It was such an emotional thing for us, we were about to forget our Salah(صلاة)
نُفتَنُ عن صلاتِنا
It was going to be a Fitnah(فِتْنَه) for us in our Salah(صلاة).
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه after he completed the Salah(صلاة)
he went to his daughter Ayesha رضي الله عنها and said;
It seems that Rasool Allah ﷺ is getting better.
So I'm going to go to my wife in As-Sunh(ألصنح).
At that time Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) had two wives,
one wife in Madina and one wife in As-Sunh(ألصنح)
which was on the outskirts of Madina.
So when he saw Rasool Allah ﷺ standing up and looking at them in Salah(صلاة)
he felt that Rasool Ullah is getting better so I can go to As-Sunh(ألصنح) and that is her turn.
Because he would spend one night here one night there. He said: This is her turn
so he went to As-Sunh(ألصنح).
But actually, Rasool Allah ﷺ was towards the last hours of his life.
After Rasool Allah ﷺ saw the Sahabah(صحابه)
and Allah comforted his heart in seeing the fruit of his Da'wah(دعوة).
The burden of the illness was taking its toll on Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Usama Bin Zayd(أسامه بن زيد) came in and Rasool Allah ﷺ was now unable to speak.
Ayesha(عائشه) said: Rasool Allah ﷺ would raise his hand
and then he would put it on Usama Bin Zayd(أسامه بن زيد)
and then he would raise his hand and put it on Usama Bin Zayd(أسامه بن زيد).
Ayesha(عائشه) said: We knew that Rasool Allah ﷺ was making Dua(دُعَا) for him.
Rasool Allah ﷺ loved Usama Bin Zayd(أسامه بن زيد) so much, he said:
ألحب إبن ألحب
He is the Beloved, the son of the Beloved
I loved his father and I loved him
and Rasool Allah ﷺ actually adopted his father as his own son
until adoption in that particular way was banned in Islam
where the person changes their name
but Rasool Allah ﷺ loved Usama(أسامه) so much he was making Dua(دُعَا) for him.
And then Ayesha(عائشه) said: So I held Rasool Allah ﷺ in my arms.
وكان بين صحري ونحري
So I was holding Rasool Allah ﷺ in my arms and he was between the bottom and the top of my chest
and I was holding him in my lap.
And then my brother Abdur Rahman(عبدالرحمن) came in and he had a Miswak(مسواك) with him.
So Rasool Allah ﷺ was looking at the Miswak(مسواك)
I realized that Rasool Allah ﷺ wants it.
So I told him: Do you want it, Rasool Ullah nodded with his head yes.
So Ayesha(عائشه) said: I took the Miswak(مسواك) from Abdur Rahman(عبدالرحمن)
and I chewed it until I made it soft.
And then I gave it to Rasool Allah ﷺ and he held it with his hand
and he brushed his teeth, as if he was healthy.
And all throughout, when he was using Miswak(مسواك), he was saying:
بَلِ الرّفيقُ الأعْلَى، بَلِ الرّفيقُ الأعْلَى، بَلِ الرّفيقُ الأعْلَى
The highest companion, the highest companion, the highest companion
Rasool Allah ﷺ was speaking to who?
He was speaking to the angel of death.
Rasool Allah ﷺ says:
Every Nabi(نَبِي) before they die the Angel of Death comes and seeks permission from them to take their soul.
See with you the angel of death will come unannounced and take it and leave.
But with the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء) of Allah, out of respect for them.
The Angel of Death asks them for permission first
and that's when Musa(موسى) punched the angel of death in the well known story in Bukhari(بخاريْ).
Rasool Allah ﷺ was saying:
بَلِ الرّفيقُ الأعْلَى
The highest companion, the highest companion, the highest companion.
Rasool Ullah was asking the question of the angel of death and saying I want to be with Allah,
the highest companion is Allah.
I want to be with Allah, I'm ready to leave, I finished my mission.
The Deen(دِيْن) is complete.
اَلْيَوْمَ أَكْمَلْتُ لَكُمْ دِينَكُمْ وَأَتْمَمْتُ عَلَيْكُمْ نِعْمَتِي وَرَضِيتُ لَكُمُ الْإِسْلَامَ دِينًا
And then Ayesha رضي الله عنها said: Rasool Allah ﷺ would say
أللهم أغفرلي ورحمني ولحقني رفيق الأعلى
O Allah forgive me and have mercy on me
and make me join the highest companion, Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ.
Ayesha رضي الله عنها said and then Rasool Allah ﷺ raised up his hand
and he would say;
اللهم الرّفيقُ الأعْلَى
The highest companion, the highest companion, the highest companion
until she says his hand went down.
And these were his last words
مَن أحَبَّ لقاءَ اللهِ أحَبَّ اللهُ لقاءَه
The one, who loves to meet Allah, Allah would love to meet him.
Rasool Allah ﷺ was eager to meet his Lord
and Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ was eager to meet Muhammadﷺ.
This is the greatest disaster that has occurred to the Ummah(امة).
In the narration, it states, whenever one of you is afflicted with a calamity
then remember your calamity in losing me
your calamity will become insignificant to you.
If you ever go through trouble, if you ever go through a problem in your life
remember that the biggest problem of all, the biggest disaster that happened to you
is that Rasool Allah ﷺ passed away.
If you remember that then your problem will be insignificant, it will become small.
How did the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم deal with the situation?
The Sahabah رضي الله عنهم, were very solid men, they were very strong.
They were very capable of tackling any situation
but the death of Rasool Allah ﷺ was something beyond.
So Ibn Rajab Al-Hambali(إبن رجب الأحنبلي) says;
ولم توفي رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم من طرب المسلمون
فمنهم من دوحش فخلد
ومنهم من أقعد فلم يطقد قيام
ومنهم من تقل لسانه فلم يطق الكلام
ومنهم من انکر موته بالكله
Ibn Rajab(إبن رجب) says: When Rasool Allah ﷺ died, a chaotic state ensued,
some of the Muslims, started to hallucinate
and they didn't know what they were saying.
While some of them sat down, and couldn't stand up.
Some of them, their tongues would not move so they cannot speak
and some of them refused to accept the fact that he died.
And Al-Qazi Abu Bakr Ibn Arabi(ألقاضي ابوبكرإبن عربي) he states, he said;
وطرف الحال فكان موت النبي قاسمة الزهري ومصيبت الأمر
And a chaotic stage happened
The death of Rasool Allah ﷺ was the event that broke their backs
and was the disaster of their lives.
أمَّا علي فستخفى بيت فاطمه
Ali(علي) went into hiding in the house of Fatima(فاطمه)
وامَّا عثمان  فسكت
And Uthman(عثمان) couldn't speak
وأمَّا عمر فأهجر وقال ما مات رسول الله
وإنَّما وعده ربه كما وعد موسى
وليرجعن رسول الله فاليقطعن ايدي رجالٍ وأرجلهم
And Umar(عُمَر) went as far as claiming that Rasool Allah ﷺ did not die
and he went to meet Allah for 40 days and he will come back
and he will cut the feet and the arms of some people who claim that he died.
So this was a very difficult time in their lives
and Anas Ibn Malik(أنس إبن مالك) says: I've seen two days in Madina.
One day was the best day in Madina and that's when Rasool Allah ﷺ came.
Everybody was happy, and Madina was full of light.
And then I've witnessed and lived through the day when Rasool Allah ﷺ died
and Madina became dark.
The light was the light of Rasool Allah ﷺ and when he died the light went.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) was at As-Sun'h(ألصنح).
He received the news, so he came riding his horse straight to the room of Ayesha رضي الله عنها.
And he came to Rasool Allah ﷺ and uncovered his face
and he kissed him on the forehead, and said: You are pure
when you're alive, and you are pure, when you're dead.
And he said: You have went through the death, which Allah has destined for you.
And then he went to the Masjid(مسجد)
while Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) was speaking.
And when Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه started to talk
Everyone left Umar(عُمَر) and they came to listen to Abu Bakr(ابوبكر).
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه said;
من كان يعبد محمداً فإن محمداً قد مات
ومن كان يعبد الله فإن الله حي لا يموت
وَمَا مُحَمَّدٌ إِلاَّ رَسُولٌ قَدْ خَلَتْ مِنْ قَبْلِهِ الرُّسُلُ
أَفَإِنْ مَاتَ أَوْ قُتِلَ انْقَلَبْتُمْ عَلَى أَعْقَابِكُمْ
وَمَنْ يَنْقَلِبْ عَلَى عَقِبَيْهِ فَلَنْ يَضُرَّ اللهَ شَيْئًا وَسَيَجْزِي اللهُ الشَّاكِرِين۝
A very brief speech, but it was a turning point in the history of this Ummah(امة), a few words.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه said: If you were worshipping Muhammad(محمد) then Muhammad(محمد) is dead.
But if you're worshipping Allah than Allah is alive and He never dies.
And then he recited the Ayah(آية), one, forty four(144) of Surat Al-Imram(سورة ألعمران)
Muhammad(محمد) is not but a messenger, other messengers have passed on before him.
So if he was to die, or to be killed, would you turn back on your heels to unbelief.
And he who turns back on his heels will never harm Allah at all.
But Allah will reward the grateful.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said: When I heard that Ayah(آية)
from the mouth of Abu Bakr(ابوبكر).
It was as if it was the first time I ever hear the Ayah(آية).
Even though Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) was a Hafiz(حافظ) of Qur'an.
But he didn't imagine that the death of Rasool Allah ﷺ would happen at that moment.
Now this Ayah(آية) was revealed in the Ghazwa(غزوة) of Uhud(أحَد)
when there was a rumor that Rasool Allah ﷺ was killed in the battle.
So some of the Sahabah(صحابه) sat down when they heard that rumor in Uhud(أحَد) and said;
We're not gonna fight, why should we fight when Muhammadﷺ was killed, we should just stay here.
So Allah is telling them, and if Muhammadﷺ is killed or he dies
you would go back to unbelief, even if he dies, you have to carry on with your message
and fight on what Muhammadﷺ was fighting on.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said: When I heard Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) recite that Ayah(آية)
my feet failed, my legs fails to carry me so I fell down on my knees
and I realized that Muhammadﷺ was dead.
Imagine Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) the strong powerful man
his feet wouldn't carry him anymore so he falls down, on his knees.
The narrator says, and then you could only hear crying in the Masjid(مسجد).
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه, was the one, who brought them back to reality.
And Al-Qurtubi(ألقرطبي) says: This is an evidence that Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) has the strongest heart,
because who was the one closest to Muhammadﷺ?
it was Abu Bakr(ابوبكر).
So if there was going to be anyone who should have failed in this situation,
because of the weight of it, it would have been Abu Bakr(ابوبكر),
because he was the one, who loved Rasool Allah ﷺ
and has been associated with him more than anybody else.
Nevertheless, he was the one, who brought them back and unified the Sahabah(صحابه)
and made them realize that yes, this was the Qadar(قَدَر) of Allah and it happened.
And this is one of the standing moments in the life of Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه
a very short speech, but it was a turning point, for the Ummah(امة).
Later on that day, Monday, same day, the Ansaar رضي الله عنهم
the Ansaar رضي الله عنهم, started gathering in Saqeefat Banni Sa'adah(ثقيقة بني سعدة)
a shed, belonging to Bannu Sa'ada(بنوسعدة), a meeting place.
In the beginning it was Al-Aos and Al-Khazraj(ألأوس والخزرج)
and then Al-Aos(ألأوس) left and it was only Al-Khazraj(ألخزرج).
What were they discussing?
They were discussing appointing an Ameer(أمير).
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) was busy with the burial proceedings of Rasool Allah ﷺ when somebody came and called him.
Umar(عُمَر) said: I'm busy.
The man said: Come out because something important has happened
Al-Ansaar(أنْصَار) have gathered in the portico in the Saqeefah(ثقيفه) of Bannu Sa'adah(بنوسعدة).
And war could breakout.
Al-Ansaar(ألأنْصَار) were two tribes Al-Aos Wal-Khazraj(ألأوس والخزرج) they fought each other for ages
and it was Rasool Allah ﷺ who brought them together.
And Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ) can come in any moment and cause Fitnah(فِتْنَه) between people.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) went out, and this is in one narration.
In the narration of Bukhari(بخاريْ),
it was Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) and Umar(عُمَر) who went to Al-Ansaar(ألأنْصَار) in Saqeefat Banni Sa'adah(ثقيقة بني سعدة).
When they were going there they met with two men from Al-Aos(ألأوس).
They told them: Where are you going?
Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) and Umar(عُمَر) said: We're going to the meeting place of Al-Ansaar(ألأنْصَار).
They said: Don't worry about it.
You go ahead and make your decision, Al-Muhajiroon(ألمهاجرون)
- go ahead and make your decision.
And don't worry about Al-Ansaar(ألأنْصَار), and their gathering.
Meaning this affair belongs to Al-Muhajireen(مهاجرين)
you go ahead and make the decision
you don't have to go and meet with Al-Ansaar(ألأنْصَار) at this moment.
Umar(عُمَر) said: No! We will go to them, because it is Shura(شورى)
we're not going to make our decision on our own.
We're gonna, it's going to be through Shura(شورى), so they went in to Al-Khazraj(ألخزرج).
There was somebody sitting among them who was covered, in a blanket.
So Umar(عُمَر) said: Who's that?
They said: This is Sa'ad Ibn Ubadah(سعدإبن عبادة), and he is ill
he had a fever and he was very ill.
Sa'ad Ibn Ubadah(سعدإبن عبادة) was the leader of Al-Khazraj(ألخزرج)
And he was the one, they wanted to appoint as Ameer(أمير).
Sa'ad Ibn Ubadah(سعدإبن عبادة) was a very well known figure among Al-Ansaar(ألأنْصَار)
and Rasool Allah ﷺ loved him very much.
And they wanted to appoint him as a leader for the Muslim community.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said: We went in and we sat down.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said: And I was preparing a speech
I was bringing together a speech to present.
So he was preparing, what to say.
He said: And then the Speaker of Al-Ansaar(ألأنْصَار) stood up.
This was a formal meeting so one speaker from Al-Ansaar(ألأنْصَار) would stand
and he praise Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ that's how they would start
their Khut'ba(خطبة), their talk by the Al-Hamdulillah(ألحمدلله), praising Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ
and making Salah(صلاة) on Muhammadﷺ.
And then he said;
نحن الأنصار
We the Ansaar(أنْصَار), are the helpers of Allah
Ansaar(أنْصَار), that's the meaning of Ansaar(أنْصَار), the helpers.
وكَتِيْبَةُ الْإسلام
And we are the battalion of Islam, we are the army of this religion
while Al-Muhajiroon(ألمهاجرون) are a few immigrants, small in number who left their people.
But now they want to strip away from us, this authority.
In other words, this man was saying
that the leadership of the community should now transfer to the Ansaar(أنْصَار) after Rasool Allah ﷺ.
And he says that, Al-Ansaar(ألأنْصَار) are the army of Islam while Muhajiroon(ألمهاجرون) are few in number
and that's true Al-Muhajiroon(ألمهاجرون) were much few in terms of numbers
they were way less compared to Al-Ansaar رضي الله عنه
in every battle, the Ansaar(أنْصَار) would be the majority the Muhajiroon(ألمهاجرون) are the minority
and this Hadith(حديث) is in Bukhari(بخاريْ).
In other words he's saying that we should give Baiyah(بَيْعة) to Saad Ibn Ubadah(سعدبن عبادة).
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) stood up to speak
because he has already prepared the speech.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) said: Umar(عُمَر), take it easy and sit down,
until I deliver my speech and complete it and then say whatever you want.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said;
وكنت أداري منه بعد الحد
And because of the temper of Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) I didn't want to anger him so I sat down.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه stood up and he started to speak.
Among the things he said,
maybe not all of this speech has survived
because there's bits and pieces in different narrations, he said;
And what you have mentioned about yourself, the Ansaar(أنْصَار) is undeniable
that's the truth.
When you say that you are the army of Islam, that's the truth.
When you are the helpers of Allah, that's the truth.
And he added to that by narrating the Ayaat(آيات)
and the Ahadith(احاديث) that were praising Al-Ansaar(ألأنْصَار).
And he said that Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
If the Ansaar(أنْصَار) would take one way,
while all of the other people take another way
I will follow the way of Al-Ansaar(ألأنْصَار).
And Rasool Allah ﷺ said that I am with you
my life and my death will be among Al-Ansaar(ألأنْصَار).
And when Rasool Allah ﷺ opened Makkah, he refused to go back to Makkah
and he went back with Al-Ansaar(ألأنْصَار) to Madina.
So Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) brought up all of these Ahadith(احاديث), praising Al-Ansaar(ألأنْصَار).
But then he said: But the Arabs will never approve leadership in the hands of anyone but the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
The Arabs were divided tribes and every tribe had his own pride.
And it's very difficult to bring them together
and Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) is saying that the only people
whom the Arabs would be willing to submit to, are the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
Because Quraish(قُرَيْشْ), it has been established in their hearts
that they are the nobility of Arabia and they are the protectors of Al-Haram(ألحرم).
And then Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق), he held up the hands of Umar(عُمَر) and Abu Obaidah(ابوعبيدة) and he said;
And I would be satisfied with either one of these two men being our Ameer(أمير)
so give Baiyah(بَيْعة) to whichever one you want.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said;
Everything that I wanted to say in my prepared speech
Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) has said it, and better in his impromptu speech.
He said: I was preparing this speech and thinking about it
all throughout the way until I got there.
Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) he said it, in a better way and a more complete way
and he added to add things that I have missed in an impromptu speech.
He said: The only thing that I didn't like was his last statement
asking to give a Baiyah(بَيْعة) to me.
And then Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said and
Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله) look at the statement, he said;
In the Name of Allah, I would rather be taken ahead and beheaded
then become an Ameer(أمير), over people and Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) is one of them.
I would never want to be a leader of Abu Bakr(ابوبكر).
I would rather die than assume leadership over Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه.
He saw it as inappropriate.
How could I be in the position of leadership and Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) is behind me.?
He said: I would rather die, they cut my neck.
Al-Khabbab Bin Mundhir(ألخباب بن منذر) stood up and said;
I have a solution, he is one of Al-Ansaar(ألأنْصَار).
How about a Muhajiroon(مهاجرون) appoint an Ameer(أمير) and we appoint an Ameer(أمير).
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said: You cannot have two swords in one sheath
two swords can't go together, it has to be one leader.
And then there was an argument that happened
and the voices were being raised.
So Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said: I feared Fitnah(فِتْنَه).
So I went ahead and told Abu Bakr(ابوبكر),
Extend your hand forward so I will give you Baiyah(بَيْعة).
And then I gave my Baiyah(بَيْعة) to Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه.
And then the Muhajiroon(مهاجرون) followed
and then the Ansaar(أنْصَار) came and gave him Baiyah(بَيْعة)
and they were doing it with such emotions
because they came to realize that yes, how could we appoint an Ameer(أمير), and Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) is around.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) later on, said:
يا معشرالأنصار ألستم تعلمون أنَّ رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم امارة ابوبكرأن يا أمة با الناس
فايكم تطيب نفسه ان يتقدم ابا بكر
He said: O people of Al-Ansaar(ألأنْصَار)
Don't you know that Rasool Allah ﷺ has appointed Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) to be our Imam(اِمَام)
who of you can stand ahead and be an Imam(اِمَام)
while Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) is Ma'moor(معمور).
Rasool Allah ﷺ has appointed him to be our Imam(اِمَام) in Salah(صلاة)
and the Khalifah(خليفه) will be the one, who will be Imam(اِمَام) of Salah(صلاة).
Can any one of you lead Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) in Salah(صلاة). They said:
نعوذوبالله
We seek refuge in Allah.
So they came back to realize that it is Abu Bakr(ابوبكر), who should be the Khalifah(خليفه)
so they all jumped on Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) to give him Baiyah(بَيْعة)
and they were stepping over Saad Ibn Ubadah(سعد إبن عبادة), who was ill.
And they were saying be careful, you're going to kill Saad Ibn Ubadah(سعد إبن عبادة)
so this wasn't nationalism or tribalism.
They were searching for the truth and whenever they would find it
they would hold on to it.
A few notes on the affair of the Saqeefat Bannu Sa'adah(ثقيفة بنوسعدة).
First of all, both Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) Umar  رضي الله عنهما were not seeking leadership.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) as we have mentioned he said:
I would rather be beheaded, rather than assume leadership over Abu Bakr(ابوبكر)
while Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه said, in a Khut'ba(خطبة). He said:
والله ما كنت حريصًا على العِمارة يومًا ولا ليلةً قط
He said: I've never been eager to become an Ameer(أمير), in any night or in any day
ولا كنت فيها راغبًا
And I have never wanted it to come to me
ولا سعلته الله عزَّوَجل في سرٍّ وعلانية
And I have never prayed to Allah to make me an Ameer(أمير) in public or in private
ولكني أشفقتم من الفتنة
But I was afraid that it would become a Fitnah(فِتْنَه)
I was afraid of disunity among the Ummah(امة) and that's why I accepted it
I accepted it for the benefit of the Ummah(امة).
ومالي في إمارة في المراء
And I'm having no rest, I'm having no peace of mind in this position of leadership.
ولكن قلت أمرًا عظيمًا مالي بهم من طاقة،
ولا يده إلَّا بتقوية الله عزوجل ولا ودت أنَّ أقو الناس عليها ماكان
And he said: I have no ability to bear this responsibility, unless Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ gives me strength
and I am desiring that somebody is stronger than me, would take it from me.
They didn't want to become leaders, they weren't seeking Imarah(إمارة)
Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) says that the reason I accepted it, is to keep the Ummah(امة) away from Fitnah(فِتْنَه).
When Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه said that
people would not submit, except to Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
There are actually a Hadith(حديث) in that narrated by 40 Among the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم,
many narrations one of them, that the leadership is in Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
إنَّ هذالأمر في قريش
This affair is in the hands of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
That is because of their status.
So Rasool Allah ﷺ said that the position of Khilafah(خِلَافَه) and this is only Khilafah(خِلَافَه)
it's not talking about other positions of leadership.
It is strictly speaking about the position of Khalifah(خليفه)
the highest position, Khifat(خلافت) Rasool Allah ﷺ.
The Ahadith(احاديث) that indicated the Khilafah(خِلَافَه) of Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه.
There are many indications and hints to the Khilafah(خِلَافَه) of Abu Bakr(ابوبكر).
Number one: This Hadith(حديث) is in, Muslim(مسلم)
أَتَتِ امْرَأَةٌ النبيَّ صَلَّى اللهُ عليه وسلَّمَ، فأمَرَهَا أنْ تَرْجِعَ إلَيْهِ
قَالَتْ: أرَأَيْتَ إنْ جِئْتُ ولَمْ أجِدْكَ؟ كَأنَّهَا تَقُولُ: المَوْتَ
قَالَ صَلَّى اللهُ عليه وسلَّمَ: إنْ لَمْ تَجِدِينِي فَأْتي أبَا بَكْرٍ
A women came to Rasool Allah ﷺ
Rasool Allah ﷺ made an appointment with her and told her to come back
it's either a question or a certain thing that she needed.
Rasool Allah ﷺ told her, come back and he made an appointment with her.
She said: O Messenger of Allah, what if I didn't find you.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: If you don't find me, then go to Abu Bakr(ابوبكر).
Ibn Hajar Al-Asqalani(إبن حجرألعسقلاني), he says;
وفي الحديث أنَّا مواعيد النبي كانت على من يتول الخلافة بعده تنجيزها
وفيه ردٌّ على شيعة في زعمِهم أنَّه نسَّها إستخلاف علي والعبَّاس
Ibn Hajar Al-Asqalani(إبن حجرألعسقلاني), says:
In this Hadith(حديث) is an evidence that the appointments of Rasool Allah ﷺ are to be carried on by the Khalifah(خليفه) after him.
And the Khalifah(خليفه) after him is Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) and here is a response to Shia(شيعة),
who claim that the Khalifah(خليفه) should have Ali(علي) or Al-Abbas(العباس).
This is a very interesting point made by Ibn Hajar Al-Asqalani(إبن حجرألعسقلاني).
He says that this is a clear indication that Rasool Allah ﷺ considers his deputy
the one to take responsibility in his absence is Abu Bakr(ابوبكر).
Rasool Allah ﷺ has already made it clear that the Imam(اِمَام) in Salah(صلاة) is Abu Bakr(ابوبكر)
and Salah(صلاة) is؛ the religion.
Now this woman came to Rasool Allah ﷺ, maybe for a Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) issue.
Either she wants Sadaqah(صدقة) or she has a question or...
And Rasool Allah ﷺ is telling her, if you don't find me then go to Abu Bakr(ابوبكر).
So Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) is the leader in the Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) affairs
and in the religious affairs, in both.
And in Islam they were combined
so the Imam(اِمَام) of the Salah(صلاة) is the leader of the community.
So it's very clear evidence that Rasool Allah ﷺ was actually saying
the one who should assume the responsibility after me, is Abu Bakr(ابوبكر).
If you don't find me, then go to Abu Bakr(ابوبكر).
Number two, Hudaifah رضي الله عنه said, and this Hadith(حديث) is in Tirimdi(ترمذي).
He said: We were sitting with Rasool Allah ﷺ in a gathering.
So he said: I don't know how long I will last among you
but follow the two, who will come after me
and he pointed Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) and Umar(عُمَر).
And he said: And hold on to the covenant of Ammar(عَمَّار).
And whatever Ibn Masood(إبن مسعود) narrates of my Hadith(حديث), then believe in it.
Now Rasool Allah ﷺ was pointing to Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) and Umar(عُمَر)
and say follow their way, meaning these are the leaders after me.
Number three, Abu Hurairah رضي الله عنه narrates and this Hadith(حديث) is in Muslim(مسلم).
Rasool Allah ﷺ saw a dream,
Rasool Allah ﷺ saw that he was sitting next to a pool,
and he was drawing water for the people to drink.
In the old days, you'd have a pool next to the well.
So you'd draw water out of the well and you would pour it in the pool
so people would drink directly from the pool.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: I was drawing out water from the well
and pouring it into my pool.
And then Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه wanted me to rest
so he held the bucket, and he started pulling out water
and then Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
وفي نضعه ضعف ولله يغفروله
And his pulling was weak, my Allah forgive him.
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ says;
And then Umar(عُمَر) came and he took the bucket from Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق).
So Rasool Allah ﷺ says: I have never seen a man stronger in drawing out the water like Umar(عُمَر)
and when he left the pool was flowing with water and it was splashing.
Ash-Shafie(ألشافعي) gives an interpretation to this dream. He says;
رؤیاء الأنبياء وحي
The dreams of the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء), are a form of Revelation.
When Rasool Allah ﷺ said: And there was weakness in the drawing of Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق).
It means that his time in Khilafah(خِلَافَه) will be very short, it won't be long.
And that he will be busy with the Harb(حرب) of Riddah(ردة).
So he's not going to make a lot of opening,
so he's not going to spread the water all over.
See, the water from the well is the religion of Islam.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) his Khilafah(خِلَافَه) was very short.
And he didn't have a chance to spread out the religion very far
because he only became a Khalifah(خليفه) for a little over two years.
And then Ash-Shafie(ألشافعي) says;
الذي بلغ وعمرفي طول مدت
His Khalifah(خليفه) wasn't as long as Khilafah(خِلَافَه) of Umar(عُمَر)
and Umar(عُمَر) devoted his time in Khilafah(خِلَافَه) to spreading out the message.
Jihad(جهاد) against the enemies of Allah and spreading the Deen(دِيْن) of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ
and that's how the water filled the pool and it was splashing out.
So it's considered that this Hadith(حديث) is also an indication that Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) is the next Khalifah(خليفه),
and he will be followed by Umar Ibn Al-Khattab رضي الله عنه.
Number four, and this is a Muslim(مسلم) too.
Ayesha رضي الله عنها said;
Rasool Allah ﷺ told me, when he was ill.
Call your father Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) and call your brother Abdur Rahman(عبدالرحمن),
so that I can write a covenant, a will.
Because I'm afraid that somebody might desire this
and say that it is more appropriate for me to be in this position.
But Allah, and the believers, only want Abu Bakr(ابوبكر)
Allah and the believers only want Abu Bakr(ابوبكر).
Rasool Ullah was saying hand me a paper so that I will write down a document
stating that the Khalifah(خليفه) after me is Abu Bakr(ابوبكر)
because I'm afraid that somebody might come and try to claim it
and say that it belongs to me.
When Allah and the believers want Abu Bakr(ابوبكر).
Now that did not happened.
Rasool Allah ﷺ did not write the covenant.
And we'll talk about that later on, on the implications of that.
Number five, the Hadith(حديث) of Salah(صلاة), which she mentioned briefly.
And this is in Muslim(مسلم).
When Rasool Allah ﷺ was ill.
He asked: Did the people pray? They said: No.
They're waiting for you, so he said: Put some water for me.
So Rasool Allah ﷺ went and they would pour this water on his body to cool it down.
His temperature were very was very high so he would pour a cold water on his body
but then he fell unconscious.
And when he woke up, he said: Did they pray? They said: No!
They're waiting for you, he said: Bring me water and he was trying to prepare himself for Salah(صلاة)
but every time, he would fall unconscious,
and that happened three times and then he said;
Tell Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) to lead the people in Salah(صلاة).
When they told Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) to lead the people in Salah(صلاة)
He told Umar(عُمَر), Why don't you lead them to Salah(صلاة)?
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said: No.
You should be the one, who was leading the Salah(صلاة)
So here's another indication that Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) considered
Umar(عُمَر) to be the second in command after him.
And that's why he told him to go and lead but Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said: No.
You are the one, who should be the Imam(اِمَام).
So this is other evidence that the Imam(اِمَام) of the Salah(صلاة) is the Khalifah(خليفه) of the Muslims
and Rasool Allah ﷺ clearly said that it is Abu Bakr(ابوبكر).
Number six,
The conversation that happened in the Saqeefah(ثقيفه) the Ansaar(أنْصَار) said;
One Ameer(أمير) from us and one Ameer(أمير) from you.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) told them. O, people of Al-Ansaar(الأنْصَار):
Don't you remember that Rasool Allah ﷺ has actually told Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) to lead the people in Salah(صلاة).
Who of you would like to be the Imam(اِمَام) while Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) is praying behind them.
And they said;
نعوذوبالله
We seek refuge in Allah.
We would never want to be ahead of Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه.
Number seven,
Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب), he narrates, he says;
When Rasool Allah ﷺ passed away.
And we found that he has actually appointed Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) to be the Imam(اِمَام) in the Salah(صلاة).
We said: If Rasool Allah ﷺ was pleased to have Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) lead us in our religion,
then he should also be our leader in the worldly affairs.
Because the religious affairs are higher in status
and since Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) was appointed to lead us in religion
then it only makes sense that he would also be the one to lead us in our worldly affairs.
And this is a statement by, Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب)
in Tabaqaat Ibn Sa'ad(طبقات إبن سعد).
Ahlus-Sunnah(أهل سُّنة) have two opinions regarding whether
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه was appointed by Rasool Allah ﷺ as a Khalifah(خليفه) implicitly or explicitly.
Some scholars consider all of these Ahadith(احاديث)
to hint to the appointment of Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) as Khalifah(خليفه)
and to implicitly imply that.
And this is the opinion of Al-Hasan Al-Basri(ألحسن ألبصري)
and it's also the opinion of Imam Ahmad Bin Hanbal(اِمَامْ اَحْمَدْبن حنبل).
Now, there are some scholars,
who consider the Khilafah(خِلَافَه) of Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) to be an explicit appointment by Rasool Allah ﷺ
because he made him the Imam(اِمَام) in Salah(صلاة), which means that he is the Khalifah(خليفه).
And this is the opinion of Ibn Hazm Az-Zahiri(إبن هزم ألظاهري),
and it's also the opinion of some of the scholars of Ahlul-Hadith(أهل الحديث)
and their evidence is also
إنْ لَمْ تَجِدِينِي فَأْتي أبَا بَكْرٍ
If you don't find me, then go to Abu Bakr(ابوبكر)
they consider this to be a clear cut appointment by Rasool Allah ﷺ  of Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) in the position of Khilafah(خِلَافَه).
Ibn Taymiyah(اِبْنِ تَيْمِيَّه), he comments on this by saying that
Rasool Allah ﷺ has hinted, and implied the Khilafah(خِلَافَه) of Abu Bakr(ابوبكر),
without writing it down or explicitly mentioning it.
So Ibn Taymiyah(اِبْنِ تَيْمِيَّه), he says it was the Hikma(حكمة) of Allah
that the appointment of Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) will not be done through a document
or a will by Rasool Allah ﷺ that is written
because Ibn Taymiyah(اِبْنِ تَيْمِيَّه) says: If it was done through a document
then we would say that Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) was appointed because of that document.
But the way he is appointed now is through the implications of the Hadith(حديث) of Rasool Allah ﷺ
and also through the choice of the Muslims because they gave him Baiyah(بَيْعة).
So it's combined, and it's stronger and it's also an elevation of the status of Abu Bakr(ابوبكر)
as if Ibn Taymiyah(اِبْنِ تَيْمِيَّه) is saying that it is common sense it is the expected thing to do
that it doesn't even need to be written down
it is so obvious and clear that Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) should be the Khalifah(خليفه).
There is no need for Rasool Allah ﷺ to write it down in the document.
And that did happen, and there was no dispute on the issue
and Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) was given Baiyah(بَيْعة) by the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم.
There was a private Baiyah(بَيْعة) and then there was a public Baiyah(بَيْعة) in the Masjid(مسجد),
the private Baiyah(بَيْعة) happened in the Saqeefah(ثقيفة).
And then later on, when Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) was going to give,
the first Khut'ba(خطبة) of his, as a Khalifah(خليفه)
the rest of the people came and gave him Baiyah(بَيْعة).
Now Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) how come he didn't give Baiyah(بَيْعة) to Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه
in the Saqeefah(ثقيفة), in the portico of Bannu Sa'adah(بنوسعدة).
The answer is simply because Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) was the one,
entrusted with the funeral proceedings of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
He was the closest male family relative of Rasool Allah ﷺ
therefore, he was given this responsibility of performing the burial of Rasool Allah ﷺ,
and the Baiyah(بَيْعة), of Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) happened on the same day Rasool Allah ﷺ passed away.
Rasool Allah ﷺ passed away on Monday
they gave him Baiyah(بَيْعة) on Monday.
And that's why Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) was late in giving him Baiyah(بَيْعة)
but then in the Masjid(مسجد) Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) called him forth
Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) came and he did give Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) his Baiyah(بَيْعة),
and all of the stories that Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) was hiding
and he refused to give Baiyah(بَيْعة) are false.
Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) had an excuse, in not being available
on the first day because he was busy with a burial of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
The statement of Ibn Taymiyah(اِبْنِ تَيْمِيَّه):
فلو كانت تعين مما يشتبع الأمة لو بين له رسول الله صلى الله بيان القطعًا للعزر
Ibn Taymiyah(اِبْنِ تَيْمِيَّه) says: If this was an issue of confusion
Rasool Allah ﷺ would have told the Ummah(امة), what to do would have written it down
but he says it's not an issue of confusion.
The status of Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) is so high, it's not confusing
he is the Khalifah(خليفه).
Ahlus Sunnah Wal-Jama'ah(أهل سنةوالجماعة) considered to be the consensus of the Sahabah(صحابه).
That Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) was the Khalifah(خليفه).
Saeed Bin Zaid(سعيد بن زيد) was asked:
متی بوع یا علی ابي بكر؟
When was the Baiyah(بَيْعة) given to Abu Bakr(ابوبكر).
He said: The same day Rasool Allah ﷺ passed away, because
كره أن يبقه بعديومٍ وليس في جماعة
Because the Sahabah(صحابه) did not want to stay for even one day without a Jama'ah(جماعة).
So they did it the same day Rasool Allah ﷺ passed away, even before he was buried.
You know, when we talk about the importance of Khilafah(خِلَافَه).
Rasool Allah ﷺ passed away and you had the washing of Rasool Allah ﷺ
and burial of Rasool Allah ﷺ and we know that the Sunnah(سنة) is to burry a person as fast as possible.
The burial of Rasool Allah ﷺ ended up being delayed.
He died on Monday and they say that he was buried Wednesday night.
According to some scholars, because the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم wanted to sort out the issue of Khilafah(خِلَافَه) first.
The Sahabah رضي الله عنهم who were before that, before the Da'wah(دعوة) of Muhammadﷺ
were the Arab people who were an unruly people, tribes fighting each other
very independent, they do not want to submit to any leader
but now this collective work was so ingrained in them
that they considered it to be, not appropriate for them to stay even for a day
without having an Ameer(أمير), who would run their affairs.
And they gave that precedence over washing Rasool Allah ﷺ, and burying him.
And they were discussing this issue even though their hearts were broken
because of the death of Rasool Allah ﷺ
they were discussing it the same day, and passed away.
And that shows you the importance of the issue of Khilafah(خِلَافَه) in our life
and the Muslims being in a Jama'at(جماعة),  and somebody being in the position of leadership to run and manage their affairs.
So it's iJma'ah(إجماع), of the scholars.
Al-Ba-qallani(ألبا قلاني) says:
وكان رضي الله عنه مفروض طاعة لإجماع المسلمين على طاعة
It was the Ijmah(إجماع) of the Muslims to obey Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه.
Now the issue of Khilafah(خِلَافَه) and Khalifah(خليفه) again
Al-Imam Al-Marwardi(ألإمام ألمروردي), who's considered to be one of the greatest scholars
of Islam, the classical scholars of Islam in political issues.
He wrote a book called Al-Ahkaam Al-Sultaniya(ألإحكام السلطانية), the laws of governance.
He says;
فكانت الإمامة أصلًى عليه إستقرد قواعد المِلَّةْ
The issue of having an Imam(اِمَام) and Imam(اِمَام) means, leader,
was one of the fundamentals of the religion.
and he says:
إنَّ الله جلت قدرته’ ندب الأمة زعيمًا خلف به نبوة و حاطبه الملة
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ wanted the Ummah(امة) to have a leader, who would succeed the Prophethood.
So the position of Khilafah(خِلَافَه) is so important that he is the successor of Prophethood
and he is the one, who fulfills the role that the Prophet used to fulfill, in his life.
And that's why Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه was called Khalifat Rasool Ullah(خليفة الرسول الله).
The successor of Rasool Allah ﷺ
إنْ لَمْ تَجِدِينِي فَأْتي أبَا بَكْرٍ
If you don't find me, then go to Abu Bakr(ابوبكر).
He was the deputy of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
What is the Hukum(حكم) of Khilafah(خِلَافَه)?
Is it Sunnah(سنة)?
is it the Mubah(مباح)?
is it Wajib(واجب).?
What is Hukum(حكم) of it.?
Ibn Hajr Al-Asqalani(إبن حجرألعسقلاني), he comments on the statement made by one scholar, his name is Daudi(داؤدي)
that establishing Khilafah(خِلَافَه) is Sunnah Muakkidah(سنة موكدة).
So Ibn Hajar(إبن حجر) responds to that.
Now the evidence that Ad-Daudi(ألداؤدي) uses is the fact that
the Baiyah(بَيْعة) to Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) wasn't given until hours after Rasool Allah ﷺ passed away.
So he said: Since they stayed for a few hours without a Khalifah(خليفه).
It means that it is Sunnah Muakkidah(سنة موكدة).
Ibn Hajar Al-Asqalani(إبن حجرألعسقلاني) comments on that and he says;
وَتُعقِبَةْ بالإتفاق على فرضيتها باَنَّهم تراكو لِاَجل إقَامَتَهَا اعظم المحمات وتشاغل بدفن النبي ﷺ
حتى فرغُ منهَا ومدة مزكور زمنًا يسير في بعد يومًا يُغتفرُو مثله لِإجماع الكلمة
He says: But that is not the view of the scholars
the view of the scholars, and it is their consensus, Ibn Hajar(إبن حجر) says:
Their consensus that it is mandatory that it is Fardh(فرض).
And to say that because they waited for a few hours, he said;
Waiting for a few hours to bring together the unity among the Muslims is acceptable.
If waiting for a few hours is going to bring the Ummah(امة) together and unify them, it's acceptable.
And this is the fastest possible time, they could establish the Khilafah(خِلَافَه) within a few hours.
But Ibn Hajar Al-Asqalani(إبن حجرألعسقلاني) makes it very clear that it is Fardh(فرض).
And it is the consensus of the Sahabah(صحابه) because they did it before they even buried Rasool Allah ﷺ.
We sometimes establish our religious views
based on what is the predominant case around us.
So we think, because this is how we are now, this is the right way to be
there are some people now, because there is no Imarah(عمارة) and Khilafah(خِلَافَه) in Islam today
they think that it's absolutely fine and there's no problem in that.
Brothers and Sisters, if one of the Sahabah(صحابه) was alive today they would ask Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ to take away their soul.
They would refuse to live the life that many Muslims are happy to lead today
The Sahabah رضي الله عنهم when they were in Makkah
when the Da'wah(دعوة) was starting, and there was only 38 Muslims on the face of the earth.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه went to Rasool Allah ﷺ and said;
It shouldn't be a secret Da'wah(دعوة), we have to make it public.
And as soon as the Sahabah(صحابه) reached over 100
Rasool Allah ﷺ was now starting for our base to establish his government
and move to Madina
he could have continued staying in Makkah he was protected by his uncle Al-Abbas(العباس).
Rasool Allah ﷺ was not being harmed physically.
Yes, there were threats against his life, but his Da'wah(دعوة) was going on
but Rasool Allah ﷺ for the last few years of his Da'wah(دعوة) in Makkah
was asking for Nusrah(نصرة), asking for support.
So the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم, they couldn't stand seeing Islam being humiliated
they couldn't stand seeing the Muslims being humiliated.
And now this is something perfectly normal and acceptable to some Muslims.
This is not a way of life that the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم would be happy with.
It's not even a way of life that they would be willing to live
Rasool Allah ﷺ passed away and they didn't bury him yet
and they are already meeting to discuss the issue of appointing a Khalifah(خليفه) among them.
I mean, do you understand the implications of that how important they viewed this issue.
And as the Muslim Ummah(امة) we'll continue suffering setbacks and problems
as long as we don't sort out this issue.
Look at how many family problems exist in the society
among the Muslims, I'm not talking about the non Muslims.
How many family problems are going around
how many financial problems are going around
and when I say finance problems, a person could be a millionaire but they're going to have financial problems,
because the Rizq(رزق) is coming from Haram(حرام).
How pure is the Rizq(رزق) that Muslims are making?
All of these are issues that cannot be sorted out.
Unless we establish this system, for example, take the issue of mortgage.
There is debate some say Haram(حرام), some say Halal(حلال).
You're damned if you do, you're damned if you don't
if you deal with mortgage, you're dealing with something that is Haram(حرام), Ribaa(رباء).
And if you stay away from it, then you're paying more in rent.
And Muslims want a magical solution for these problems.
There is not going to be any solution
until you bring back the law of Allah, the Hukm(حكم) of Allah in your life.
We are looking for solutions for family problems
problems between the husband and wife, problems between the children and parents
these are not going to be solved unless we're living under an Islamic system.
The Barakah(بركة) in living is, when it is under the Khilafah(خِلَافَه) of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ.
The most blessed time in the history of this Ummah(امة)
was when they were living under the Khulafaa(خلفاء) of Rasool Allah ﷺ,
Abu Bakr(ابوبكر), Umar(عُمَر), Uthman(عثمان), Ali(علي), Umar Bin Abdel-Aziz(عمربن عبدالعزيز).
So, this should be on the minds of everyone to bring back the law and the Hukum(حكم) of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ.
And on the other side if anybody thinks that Khilafah(خِلَافَه), can be established
without the path of Jihad(جهاد) is mistaken.
Because Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه says
and we'll talk about his statements in his Khut'ba(خطبة).
وما ترك قوم جهاد في سبيل الله إلَّا ذِلُّ
Any people, who leave the mandate of Jihad(جهاد), are going to be humiliated.
It's the Qadar(قَدَر) of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ, it's going to happen.
Some lessons to that could be derived from the meeting in the portico of Sa'adah(سعدة) is,
Number one, Shura(شورى) in Islam.
There's a narration, Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) says;
من دوعيَّ إلى عمارة من غير مشورى  فلا يحلُّ له أن يقبل
Whoever is asked to be in a position of leadership
without the Shura(شورى) of the Muslims, it is not Halal(حلال) for him to accept it.
If you are told come and be Ameer(أمير), and it's without the Shura(شورى) of the Muslims
don't get your feet into that pit hole.
Because Al-Imarah(ألعمارة) is Mas'ooliyah(مسئولية)
and you're going to be asked about, on the Day of Judgment.
And if it's without the Shura(شورى), of the Muslims, you should not accept it.
The Baiyah(بَيْعة) of Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) was to the Shura(شورى) of the Muslims.
Same thing with the khulafah(خلفاء) after that
so we also learned that the Khilafah(خِلَافَه) is established through Baiyah(بَيْعة)
and Rasool Allah ﷺ says in the Hadith(حديث),
ومن مات وليس في عنقه بيعة مات ميتة جاهلية
If you die, without a pledge of allegiance to the Imam(اِمَام) you are dying in a state of Jahiliyyah(جَاهلِيَّة).
Now this is strictly speaking about the Khalifah(خليفه) too.
This is not talking about presidents and kings or local leaders,
it's talking about the Khalifah(خليفه), the Baiyah(بَيْعة).
Al-Baiyah Al-Uzma(ألبَيْعة العظمى) this Baiyah(بَيْعة) that Rasool Allah ﷺ is referring to is about Al-Khilafah (خِلَافَه)
and since there is no Khilafah(خِلَافَه) now.
Then we are living in an exception of this rule
until the Khalifah(خليفه) exists, then the Hadith(حديث) would apply again.
Also, we learn that the issue of bringing up Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه bringing up Quraish(قُرَيْشْ)  is because it's a practical issue, it's a realistic issue
and this needs to be taken into consideration in Islamic work.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه is saying;
The nature of the Arabs is that they wouldn't accept a leader from outside Quraish(قُرَيْشْ)
so one needs to take into consideration, the nature of the people
one needs to take into consideration, what is possible and what is not possible
and not try to be idealistic and unrealistic in their affairs and in their Da'wah(دعوة).
This is beyond the scope of these talks on Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه.
But Ibn Khaldoon(إبن خلدون) has a lot to say about this issue of how come Quraish(قُرَيْشْ)
and he talks about the issue of Usbah(عصبة) the strength
and the support that is given by the tribe
he talks about that in his book Al-Muqaddimah(ألمقدمه).
صَلَّى الله عَلى سَيَّدِنَا محمد وَعَلى اَلِهِ وَ صَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ